<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>youkwhd's blog posts</title>
        <link>http://localhost:3000</link>
        <description>an archive consist of articles from youkwhd's site</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 04:35:50 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <copyright>All rights reserved 2022, youkwhd</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What makes a GNU/Linux rice looks good]]></title>
            <link>http://localhost:3000/blog/what-makes-a-gnu-linux-rice-looks-good</link>
            <guid>http://localhost:3000/blog/what-makes-a-gnu-linux-rice-looks-good</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2022 18:03:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[I remembered my first time ricing my Ubuntu using vanilla i3 and eventually switched to i3-gaps that makes things a little bit spicy. but still, my GNU/Linux still feels plain. nothing fancy about it, not even compareable to r/unixporn posts]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I remembered my first time ricing my Ubuntu using vanilla i3 and eventually switched to i3-gaps that makes things a little bit spicy. but still, my GNU/Linux still feels plain. nothing fancy about it, not even compareable to r/unixporn posts.</p>
<h2 id="table-of-contents">Table of contents</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="#window-managers-doesnt-affect-anything">Window Managers doesn't affect anything</a></li>
<li><a href="#things-that-really-makes-it-perfect">Things that really makes it perfect</a></li>
<li><a href="#add-some-gaps-even-if-its-small">Add some gaps even if it's small</a></li>
<li><a href="#use-colorized-or-plain-wallpapers">Use colorized or plain wallpapers</a></li>
<li><a href="#determine-your-terminal-transparency-and-prompt">Determine your terminal transparency and prompt</a></li>
<li><a href="#x-bar-status">X Bar status</a></li>
<li><a href="#rounded-terminal-shadow-and-outline">Rounded terminal, shadow and outline</a></li>
<li><a href="#keep-the-theme-on-fit">Keep the theme on fit</a></li>
<li><a href="#conclusion">Conclusion</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="window-managers-doesnt-affect-anything">Window Managers doesn't affect anything</h2>
<p>Well, i like suckless softwares; dwm, dmenu, st, etc. It suck less, non bloated, then the way it's configured, the patches that is available, and it is widely customizable. What about other Window Managers? they all the same, it's just the programming language that's differ from others, the way it's configured, the maintainer, functionality. But really, when it comes to ricing, it does not matter.</p>
<p>take a look at my recent linux rice:</p>
<p><img src="/assets/blog/wm__screenshot-03.png" alt="youkwhd&#x27;s GNU/Linux rice"></p>
<p>the color scheme matched the wallpaper in the background, st has transparency, then there's big gaps in between. Also, the font matched with the environment.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>here are my <a href="https://github.com/youkwhd/dotfiles">dotfiles</a> configs.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>the fact is that i can make the same layout using i3, i mean the <strong>exact same</strong> as the screenshot above. Now we know that any Window Managers are viable. Use the one that you comfort to use with.</p>
<h2 id="things-that-really-makes-it-perfect">Things that really makes it perfect</h2>
<p>After months of ricing GNU/Linux, now i can share the things i think really makes the difference. These are my thoughts on why some GNU/Linux rice looks bad.</p>
<p>take a look at my first rice, i was using vanilla i3 at that time:</p>
<p><img src="/assets/blog/wm__screenshot-04.png" alt="youkwhd&#x27;s first GNU/Linux rice"></p>
<p>what do you see? Gruvbox. Nothing but a fullscreen terminal with i3status on top, no gaps, nothing. Straight plain.</p>
<p>what about the color scheme, isn't Gruvbox a good color scheme? yes indeed. I personally like it. But i wouldn't ever again staring at a fullscreen terminal, it just doesn't feel good.</p>
<p>then i switched to i3-gaps, it looks far more better, it is an ok environment. But i don't have any wallpaper installed. As you can guess, there is nothing but a blank black wallpaper and a non-transparent terminal. The result is still as bad.</p>
<p>Note that the font is an ok option in this case. Take a look at the i3status, one icon, then all the number stuff? what does the GiB section even mean? is it how much memory left? what is that? it confuses you. Plus the size of the i3status doesn't fit with the i3-gaps font base.</p>
<p>at that time, i thought i've made my rice to be as perfect as i want. But as time flies, i realize that this is beyond perfect, nothing special.</p>
<h2 id="add-some-gaps-even-if-its-small">Add some gaps even if it's small</h2>
<p>you will feel better if you add gaps. Just, trust me. It's the UI/UX thing. even a little bit of gaps can change the feel, just maybe 5 pixels for each window. I promise your WM will look better and fresh.</p>
<p>take a look at my i3 config as if it has some gaps:</p>
<p><img src="/assets/blog/wm__screenshot-05.png" alt="youkwhd&#x27;s i3-gaps"></p>
<p>you've made some progress, and you've successfully made your window manager better.</p>
<h2 id="use-colorized-or-plain-wallpapers">Use colorized or plain wallpapers</h2>
<p>what you will regularly actually see is the background. Really tho, use one that looks super cool and the one that matches your style preferences. In case if you don't like to use wallpapers, you can use any plain wallpaper as an alternative. if you did used a plain wallpaper, you might want to match the terminal background color.</p>
<p>for an example; if i use a plain black wallpaper, then the terminal background saturation should be a little bit higher, still black but has more saturation on it.</p>
<h2 id="determine-your-terminal-transparency-and-prompt">Determine your terminal transparency and prompt</h2>
<p>you can have a non-transparent terminal but under a certain conditions, e.g the terminal background color must be pure black, then add paddings inside the terminal so it'll look more minimalist, or even add a border radius, and you can also put a very standing border color like pure white. Also, consider the prompt (PS1) to be minimal as well. for example:</p>
<p><code>export PS1="\W > \[$(tput sgr0)\]"</code></p>
<p>thus will render out:</p>
<pre><code>~ > echo "youkwhd.github.io" 
~ > yay -S icecat vim
</code></pre>
<blockquote>
<p>found this screenshot from the internet</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img src="/assets/blog/wm__screenshot-07.jpg" alt="terminal example"></p>
<p>the way to configure transparency, shadow, etc. Is to install a compositor for X, e.g. picom, Xcompmgr, Unagi.</p>
<p>in case if you were using cool and cozy wallpapers, then you can do something like a really long prompt, for example:</p>
<p><code>export PS1="[\u@\h \W]\$ "</code></p>
<p>the following prompt would be:</p>
<pre><code>[youkwhd@severus ~]$ echo "youkwhd.github.io"
[youkwhd@severus ~]$ yay -S icecat vim
</code></pre>
<p>if you chose to use the long-prompt-like one, then i wouldn't have to consider paddings, but it depens on your preferences. Keep experimenting and you'll eventually like it.</p>
<h2 id="x-bar-status">X Bar status</h2>
<p>your window manager bar (i3bar, dwmblocks, etc) are one of the aspect of making a good rice. A messy, gray colored font for X bar will sometimes resulting in a bad X bar, and could even make it worse to read. What you can do is to add some life into it, an example of it is to use emojis as an advantage for you to make your X bar pretty. Or you can even use font-awesome as an alternative.</p>
<h2 id="rounded-terminal-shadow-and-outline">Rounded terminal, shadow and outline</h2>
<p>as mentioned above, adding these can result a nice feel, and make your terminal stands out. Tho it's only an additional option, add what's needed and what suits your style. don't over tweak things.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>i also found this screenshot from the internet</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img src="/assets/blog/wm__screenshot-08.jpg" alt="terminal shadow and outline"></p>
<h2 id="keep-the-theme-on-fit">Keep the theme on fit</h2>
<p>You can easily generate dynamic color schemes using pywal, any other premade themes like gruvbox, dracula, etc. Is a valid option especially if you are just getting started and wanted a stable color scheme. I don't recommend you to make your own theme / color scheme as a beginner, but rather if you are good at UI/UX or designing things, then go for it.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>here comes the conclusion, don't be afraid to change things up, especially for your own good. If you are too afraid to make a mistake, configure a virtual machine, then use it as an experiment GNU/Linux rice, tho you might have more issues with virtual machines, it's still a good alternative way to ricing.</p>
<p>keep your attention to small details like spaces in between windows. When it comes to customizing your GNU/Linux, if you ever feel like it's wonky, re-check if anything doesn't make sense, e.g; your theme doesn't match, or if it's too bright.</p>
<p>happy hacking!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>lolywk@tutanota.com (youkwhd)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Remote: support for password authentication was removed on august 13, 2021]]></title>
            <link>http://localhost:3000/blog/remote-support-for-password-authentication-was-removed</link>
            <guid>http://localhost:3000/blog/remote-support-for-password-authentication-was-removed</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2021 16:34:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[as the error said "remote: support for password authentication was removed on August 13, 2021. solved" github does not support nor accept account password when authenticating git operations, now you have to use github personal access tokens.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>as the error said "remote: support for password authentication was removed on August 13, 2021" github does not support nor accept account password when authenticating git operations, now you have to use github personal access tokens. which is an alternative for password auth.</p>
<h2 id="table-of-contents">Table of contents</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="#creating-a-token">Creating a token</a></li>
<li><a href="#using-the-token">Using the token</a></li>
<li><a href="#github-cli-tool">Github CLI tool</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="creating-a-token">Creating a token</h2>
<p>head to github main page <a href="https://github.com">https://github.com</a></p>
<p>after entering your github profile, please head to the settings<br>
or you can open <a href="https://github.com/settings/profile">this link</a> on new tab.</p>
<p><img src="/assets/blog/github-settings.png" alt="github-settings-screenshot"></p>
<p>now you can head to the developer settings
or you can open <a href="https://github.com/settings/tokens">this link</a> on new tab.</p>
<p><img src="/assets/blog/github-dev-settings.png" alt="github-dev-settings-screenshot"></p>
<p>then you can create your own token.</p>
<p><img src="/assets/blog/github-token.png" alt="github-token-screenshot"></p>
<p>you should get this success message from github. <strong>DO NOT SHARE</strong> your own personal access token. except if it's meant for others.</p>
<p><img src="/assets/blog/github-token-success.png" alt="github-token-success-screenshot"></p>
<p>now you have successfully created your own PATs, you should be able to work with git remotely.</p>
<p>for more information, please see <a href="https://docs.github.com/en/authentication/keeping-your-account-and-data-secure/creating-a-personal-access-token">this article</a> from github.</p>
<h2 id="using-the-token">Using the token</h2>
<p>now you should be able to use the token. you should change your origin remote to:</p>
<p><code>https://&#x3C;token>@github.com/&#x3C;username>/&#x3C;repo>.git</code></p>
<h2 id="github-cli-tool">Github CLI tool</h2>
<p>try this github cli to authenticate automatically:<br>
please head to the <a href="https://cli.github.com/manual/installation">official instruction</a> to install.</p>
<p>installation for <strong>debian based</strong>:</p>
<pre><code>curl -fsSL https://cli.github.com/packages/githubcli-archive-keyring.gpg | sudo gpg --dearmor -o /usr/share/keyrings/githubcli-archive-keyring.gpg
echo "deb [arch=$(dpkg --print-architecture) signed-by=/usr/share/keyrings/githubcli-archive-keyring.gpg] https://cli.github.com/packages stable main" | sudo tee /etc/apt/sources.list.d/github-cli.list > /dev/null
sudo apt update
sudo apt install gh
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Note</strong>: If you get the error <em>"gpg: failed to start the dirmngr '/usr/bin/dirmngr': No such file or directory"</em>, try installing the <code>dirmngr</code> package: <code>sudo apt install dirmngr</code>.</p>
<p>to login, follow this code:</p>
<pre><code>gh auth login
</code></pre>
<p>then gh will ask some question, you can directly use password or PATs to authenticate. Now you've installed <code>gh</code> github cli tool. And made your first personal access token (PATs) for github. I hope it solved your problem. thank you for reading this article, happi hacking.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
            <author>lolywk@tutanota.com (youkwhd)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>